Guide to the Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence Editorial Project Records
The Lewis Walpole Library
- Editorial Documents, 1934–1982; Series II; 28.6; 70 boxes + 1 broadside
  - Volumes 3-8: Madame du Deffand
    - Correspondence, 1936–1937 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Toynbee, 1912 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      Pages removed from Mrs. Paget Toynbee's Lettres de la Marquise Du Deffand a Horace Walpole (London: Methuen et Cie, 1912), with notes by Warren H. Smith.
    - Notes, 1936–1937 (Box 14, Folder 3-4)
    - Galleys, circa 1938 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Card file, circa 1936 (Box 15)
      W. H. Smith's card index of the du Deffand correspondence, with a note by Lewis's librarian Catherine Jestin: "CJ made new cards, not knowing that these were at Room 331B" [at Sterling Memorial Library]. Jestin's cards are part of the Lewis Walpole Library's reading room reference materials.
  - Volumes 9-10: George Montagu
    - Correspondence, 1934–1940 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Notes, 1936–1939 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Front matter, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
      Autograph manuscripts, typescripts, and typescript carbons, corrected.
    - Corrections to galleys, 1940, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
      Comments and corrections by R. W. Chapman and others; galleys are not present.
  - Volumes 13-14: Thomas Gray
    - Notebooks 1-9 (Box 16, Folder 5-6)
      George L. Lam's notes on the Walpole-Gray correspondence.
  - Volumes 15-16: Thomas Chatterton and others
    - Draft and notes for introduction, circa 1950 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, lists, and notes related to illustrations, 1950 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Volumes 17-27: Sir Horace Mann
    The Walpole-Mann correspondence fills ten volumes (17-27) and was published between 1954 and 1971. In addition to W. S. Lewis, the editors were Warren Hunting Smith and George L. Lam. The annotated typescripts were retained by the library staff in 1980, with this note:
    "These folders of Mann material were the work of Warren H. Smith and George L. Lam. They are to be kept because they contain extensive research which was not incorporated into the Yale Edition of Walpole's Correspondence. Consequently, they may prove invaluable to some future researcher. In addition to the chronological folders of letters, there is some miscellaneous material to be found at the beginning and end of the chronological folders."
    Also retained by the library staff were George Lam's notebooks and other research notes, with one volume of the typed index.
    - Correspondence
      - Bagnani, Gilbert, 1954–1961 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        Biographical / Historical
        Gilbert Forrest Bagnani (1900-1985) moved from Italy to Canada in 1937, and taught ancient history at the University of Toronto.
      - Sartini, Ferdinando, 1945–1956 (Box 17, Folder 2-3)
        Ferdinando Sartini (1878-1955) was director of the State Archives in Florence.
      - Yale University Press, 1952–1970 (Box 17, Folder 4)
        Correspondence with the press primarily consists of cover letters that accompanied proofs sent from the press; they now serve to document the process and timing by which edits were made. A letter from George Lam to the press, dated January 7, 1952, reveals that eleven sets of galleys were issued, and sent to readers in England (Owen Morshead, L. B. Namier, R. W. Chapman, and R. W. Ketton-Cremer), Italy (Ferdinando Sartini), Rhode Island (Leonard Bacon), and Connecticut (Bernhard Knollenberg, Frederick Pottle, Archibald Foord, Wilmarth Lewis, and Smith and Lam).
      - Other correspondence, 1939-1972 (Box 17, Folder 5)
        Correspondence between the editorial staff and Wilmarth Lewis, as well as with scholars in England and Europe.
    - Research materials
      - Accounts for Mann and other diplomats, 1948–1949 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - Casa Ambrogi, 1947–1948 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Casa Manetti, 1945–1968 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Cue-titles, 1947–1949 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - Florentine account (Yale), 1947–1953 (Box 17, Folder 10)
        Financial records for an account set up to fund research and researchers in Italy.
      - Mann manuscript, 1947–1969 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Mann letter with "blotted out" lines, undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 4)
        Photostats of redacted correspondence.
      - Maps, undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Notes on early Medici, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - Papal conclave, 1938-1939, undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
        Contains correspondence with the Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana (Vatican Library).
      - Waller manuscript items dealing with disposition of Mann correspondence, undated (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - George L. Lam's "Commonplace Books"
      George Lorant Lam worked as an editor on volumes 13 and 14 (correspondence with Thomas Gray, Richard West and Thomas Ashton, published in 1948) but his greatest contribution to the project was in coediting Horace Walpole's correspondence with Sir Horace Mann, which was published in ten volumes between 1954 and 1971.
      Lam was born on June 4, 1909, in Hungary, and received degrees from Bowdoin College (BA 1931) and Cornell University (MA 1933, PhD 1938). He moved to New Haven in 1937 to accept a position as an assistant editor on the Walpole correspondence project. While in New Haven Lam received bachelor's and master's degrees in music from Yale, and played double bass in the New Haven Symphony. He served in the United States Army during World War II, and remained active in the reserves through 1969. Lam died in New Haven on August 21, 1970.
      Lam filled fifty-eight Yale University school composition books with his notes, and described their purpose on the flyleaf of the first volume: "Commonplace Books vol i. begun Oct 16, 1947. To contain bibliographical information, notes, etc. in connection with Mann Corr. Each item to be numbered serially in red for indexing purposes in HW Bibliography. References to be made to GLL Notebooks, vol I, item ----. Items with subdivisions will be cited ----item number, decimal point, paragraph number, e.g. 'GLL Notebooks, i. 121.2'"
      - Volumes 1-7, 1947–1950 (Box 18, Folder 1-7)
      - Volumes 8-13, 1950–1953 (Box 19, Folder 1-6)
      - Volumes 14-19, 1953–1956 (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
      - Volumes 20-25, 1956–1957 (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
      - Volumes 26-31, 1957–1961 (Box 22, Folder 1-6)
      - Volumes 32-37, 1961–1963 (Box 23, Folder 1-6)
      - Volumes 38-43, 1963–1965 (Box 24, Folder 1-6)
      - Volumes 44-49, 1965–1967 (Box 25, Folder 1-6)
      - Volumes 50-55, 1967–1969 (Box 26, Folder 1-6)
      - Volumes 56-58, 1969–1970 (Box 27, Folder 1-3)
    - Mann transcripts
      Typescript carbons of Mann correspondence, corrected and annotated. The carbons are undated but notes on and in the folders range from 1950-1966.
      - 1740 April - 1741 June (Box 28, Folder 1-8)
      - 1741 July - October (Box 29, Folder 1-6)
      - 1741 November - 1742 January (Box 30, Folder 1-5)
      - 1742 January - April (Box 31, Folder 1-7)
      - 1742 April - July (Box 32, Folder 1-6)
      - 1742 July - December (Box 33, Folder 1-9)
      - 1742 December - 1743 April (Box 34, Folder 1-8)
      - 1743 May - August (Box 35, Folder 1-7)
      - 1743 September - 1744 January (Box 36, Folder 1-6)
      - 1744 January - June (Box 37, Folder 1-7)
      - 1744 July - 1745 January (Box 38, Folder 1-7)
      - 1745 January - July (Box 39, Folder 1-7)
      - 1745 July - October (Box 40, Folder 1-8)
      - 1745 November - 1746 March (Box 41, Folder 1-7)
      - 1746 April - August (Box 42, Folder 1-8)
      - 1746 September - 1747 February (Box 43, Folder 1-7)
      - 1747 March - October (Box 44, Folder 1-9)
      - 1747 November - 1748 November (Box 45, Folder 1-11)
      - 1748 December - 1749 June (Box 46, Folder 1-9)
      - 1749 July - 1750 August (Box 47, Folder 1-14)
      - 1750 September - 1751 September (Box 48, Folder 1-13)
      - 1751 October - 1753 March (Box 49, Folder 1-14)
      - 1753 April - 1754 October (Box 50, Folder 1-15)
      - 1754 November - 1756 April (Box 51, Folder 1-15)
      - 1756 May - 1757 January (Box 52, Folder 1-10)
      - 1757 February - December (Box 53, Folder 1-11)
      - 1758 January - 1759 January (Box 54, Folder 1-13)
      - 1759 February - 1760 February (Box 55, Folder 1-13)
      - 1760 March - 1761 March (Box 56, Folder 1-13)
      - 1761 April - 1762 May (Box 57, Folder 1-14)
      - 1762 June - 1763 June (Box 58, Folder 1-13)
      - 1763 July - 1764 September (Box 59, Folder 1-15)
      - 1764 October - 1766 January (Box 60, Folder 1-15)
      - 1766 February - 1767 March (Box 61, Folder 1-13)
      - 1767 April - 1768 June (Box 62, Folder 1-11)
      - 1768 July - 1769 November (Box 63, Folder 1-12)
      - 1769 December - 1771 February (Box 64, Folder 1-14)
      - 1771 March - 1772 April (Box 65, Folder 1-13)
      - 1772 May - 1773 September (Box 66, Folder 1-14)
      - 1773 October - 1774 November (Box 67, Folder 1-14)
      - 1774 December - 1776 March (Box 68, Folder 1-16)
      - 1776 April - 1777 July (Box 69, Folder 1-16)
      - 1777 August - 1778 October (Box 70, Folder 1-15)
      - 1778 November - 1779 September (Box 71, Folder 1-11)
      - 1779 October - 1780 October (Box 72, Folder 1-11)
      - 1780 November - 1781 September (Box 73, Folder 1-11)
      - 1781 October - 1782 June (Box 74, Folder 1-9)
      - 1782 July - 1783 May (Box 75, Folder 1-11)
      - 1783 June - December (Box 76, Folder 1-6)
      - Index, W-Z (Box 76, Folder 7)
        Typescript, corrected; in original binder, with accompanying note by Lewis's librarian Catherine Jestin: "Sample of Mann Index in typescript. Keep as an example of style used ultimately for all the Index. WHS [Warren H. Smith] thought one vol. example, as example."
  - Volume 35: John Chute and others
    - Draft and notes for introduction, 1973 (Box 77, Folder 1)
  - Volumes 37-39: Henry Seymour Conway and others
    - Census of letters, undated (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - Draft and notes for introduction, 1972–1974 (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - Notes on endpapers illustrating Conway's tour, circa 1972 (Box 77, Folder 4)
      Typescript, annotated.
  - Volumes 40-42: Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Proposed printing schedule for Volumes 40-42, 1979 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Notes for introduction, 1979 (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - Volume 40: galley with W. S. Lewis's corrections, 1979 (Box 77, Folder 7)
      Accompanied by a note by Lewis's librarian Catherine Jestin: "Galley for CAG-MAG An example of editorial work, bound to preserve."
    - Volume 41: galleys with W. S. Lewis's corrections, 1979 (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - Volume 41: galleys with second corrections, 1979 (Box 77, Folder 9)
    - Volume 42: "Horace Walpole's Twickenham", 1979 (Box 83 (Broadside))
      Original artwork by Boston-area calligrapher Edith McKeon Abbott for the fold-out map appearing at the back of the volume; also present are separate prints made from the artwork.
    - Volume 42: Appendix 1, 1979 (Box 78, Folder 1)
      Typescript draft, corrected, of "Walpole's Twickenham."
    - Draft index for letters A and X-Z, 1979 (Box 78, Folder 2)
      Cards sampled from A-Z series; accompanied by a note by Lewis's librarian Catherine Jestin: "Index to CAG-MAG (text) v. 40, 41, 42 To be discarded when in print."
  - Volumes 44-48: Complete Index
    - Warren H. Smith's index for letters T and W-Z, circa 1980 (Box 78, Folder 3-4)
      Autograph manuscript on yellow lined paper.
    - Typescript carbon, carbon, for letters A and W-Z, circa 1981 (Box 78, Folder 5-6)
      Sampled from a multi-volume set of edited typescripts.
    - Report, 1982 (Box 78, Folder 7)
- The Horace Walpole Diurnal, undated; Series III; 16.22; 12 boxes
  Series IV is arranged in chronological order by content.
  In his autobiographical work Collector's Progress, Wilmarth Lewis described the contents of his library, and mentioned on p. xvii a special reference tool he had developed to track Horace Walpole's whereabouts and daily activities. As he explained, "A 'diurnal' records what is known of every day in his [Walpole's] life from his twentieth year to his eightieth."
  Lewis's calendar of Walpole's life was created on specially printed slips of paper. Each slip represents a week, and features columns in which could be entered Walpole's known location, the correspondents from whom he received or to whom he sent letters, the guests he entertained, notes on his health, and the events happening on that day. The slips and their sets of tabbed date dividers were kept in black binders made especially for the project. An ambitious undertaking, the volumes, in the end, primarily have notes on Walpole's incoming and outgoing correspondence, with occasional annotations in the other fields.
  It is not known how complete the record here is, or who did the work to fill in the sheets, but it is likely that the data in these binders was used to create the "Chronological List of Letters" found on pages 445-648 of Volume 43 of the Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence.
  - Volume covering the years 1739 through 1743, undated (Box 85 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1744 through 1748, undated (Box 86 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1749 through 1753, undated (Box 87 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1754 through 1758, undated (Box 88 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1759 through 1763, undated (Box 89 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1764 through 1768, undated (Box 90 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1769 through 1773, undated (Box 91 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1774 through 1778, undated (Box 92 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1779 through 1783, undated (Box 93 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1784 through 1788, undated (Box 94 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1789 through 1793, undated (Box 95 (Oversize))
  - Volume covering the years 1794 through 1797, undated (Box 96 (Oversize))
- Clyde S. Kilby Notes on Horace Walpole as a Literary Critic, circa 1945; Series IV; 0.21; 1 box
  Clyde Samuel Kilby (1902-1986)
  Clyde Samuel Kilby was an American author and English professor at Wheaton College in Illinois from 1935 to 1981.
  Clyde Kilby endeavored to write a book on Walpole's efforts in literary criticism but abandoned the project in 1949 and sent his notes to Lewis on the chance they could be of use in preparing the Walpole correspondence edition. As his work was incomplete, and greatly superseded by the correspondence edition's printed indexes (later, the keyword-searchable electronic edition), his notes and cards were sampled before being discarded in 2018.
  - Notes and cards, circa 1945 (Box 79, Folder 1-4)